{"test_questions": [[{"question": "The nonsymbiotic bacteria which fix nitrogen live in the soil independently are", "opta": "Azotobacter", "optb": "Clostridium", "optc": "considerably less important in comparison to the symbiotic bacteria", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nitrogen fixation by the microorganisms can be detected by adopting the approach of", "opta": "demonstrating growth in a nitrogen free medium", "optb": "cultivating the microorganisms in the presence of nitrogen labeled with isotropic nitrogen", "optc": "measuring15N2 by mass spectrometer", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is not the biofertilisers producing bacteria?", "opta": "Nostoc", "optb": "Anabaena", "optc": "Both (a) and (b)", "optd": "Clostridium", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is capable of oxidizing sulfur to sulfates?", "opta": "Thiobacillus thiooxidans", "optb": "Desulfotomaculum", "optc": "Rhodospirillum", "optd": "Rhodomicrobium", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Most soil protozoa are flagellates or amoebas, having their dominant mode of nitrogen as", "opta": "ingestion of bacteria", "optb": "ingestion of mold", "optc": "ingestion of fungi", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following microorganism use H2S as the electron donor to reduce carbon dioxide?", "opta": "Chromaticum", "optb": "Chlorobium", "optc": "Both (a) and (b)", "optd": "Rhodomicrobium", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nitrifying bacteria can not be isolated directly by the usual techniques employed to isolate hetrotrophic bacteria. The reasons may be due to", "opta": "slow growth", "optb": "medium growth", "optc": "fast growth", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Bacteria, as a group, are responsible for", "opta": "nitrogen oxidation", "optb": "sulfur oxidation", "optc": "nitrogen fixation", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The phenomenon of commensalism refers to a relationship between organisms in which", "opta": "one species of a pair benefits", "optb": "both the species of a pair benefit", "optc": "one species of a pair is more benefited", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The population of algae in soil is __________ that of either bacteria or fungi.", "opta": "generally smaller than", "optb": "generally greater than", "optc": "equal to", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The transformation of nitrates to gaseous nitrogen is accomplished by microorganisms in a series of biochemical reactions. The process is known as", "opta": "nitrification", "optb": "denitrification", "optc": "nitrogen fixation", "optd": "ammonification", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nitrogen fixation refers to the direct conversion of atmospheric nitrogen gas into", "opta": "ammonia", "optb": "glucose", "optc": "ATP", "optd": "nitrate", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The diagnostic enzyme for denitrification is", "opta": "nitrate reductase", "optb": "nitrate oxidase", "optc": "nitro oxidoreductase", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A heterocyst is", "opta": "a type of spore", "optb": "a terminally differentiated cell that fixes nitrogen", "optc": "the progenitor of cyanobacterial vegetative cells", "optd": "a cell that carries out oxygenic photosynthesis", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The groups of symbiotic bacteria, which have the ability to fix nitrogen", "opta": "derive their food and minerals from the legume, and in turn they supply the legume with some or all of its nitrogen", "optb": "grow together for a mutual benefit is called symbiosis and so these bacteria are called symbiotic nitrogen-fixing bacteria", "optc": "these bacteria are from the genus, Rhizobium", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nitrogen oxidation (nitrification)refers to the", "opta": "conversion of ammonium ions into nitrates through the activities of certain bacteria.", "optb": "changing of atmospheric nitrogen (N2) to nitrogen compounds", "optc": "sulfur is oxidized to the sulfate form through Thiobacillus bacteria", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An example of a symbiotic nitrogen fixer is", "opta": "Azotobacter", "optb": "Beijerinckia", "optc": "Clostridium", "optd": "Rhizobium", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following is correct?", "opta": "Mycorrhizae are fungi that form a mutually beneficial (symbiotic) relationship with plant roots", "optb": "The fungi aid in transmitting nutrients and water to the plant roots", "optc": "The increased nutrient availability from mycorrhizae is thought to be due to the additional absorbing surface provided by the fungi", "optd": "All of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the process of nitrogen fixation, which of the following microorganism is involved?", "opta": "Non symbiotic microorganisms only", "optb": "Symbiotic microorganisms only", "optc": "Non symbiotic and symbiotic microorganisms only", "optd": "None of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following statement is not true about composition of biogas?", "opta": "It is composed almost exclusively of methane and carbon dioxide", "optb": "It also contains with traces of H2S, N2, H2and CO", "optc": "It also contains with traces of O2 and Cl2", "optd": "Both (a) and (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The physical structure of soil is improved by the accumulation of", "opta": "mold mycelium", "optb": "minerals", "optc": "water", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "__________ play a key role in the transformation of rock to soil.", "opta": "Cyanobacteia", "optb": "Pectin decomposing bacteria", "optc": "Nitrifying bacteria", "optd": "De-nitrifying bacteria", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The groups of bacteria which have the ability to fix nitrogen from air to soil are", "opta": "symbiotic", "optb": "nonsymbiotic", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The nitrogenase consists of", "opta": "dinitrogenase", "optb": "dinitrogenase reductase", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The crops which are involved in nitrogen fixation are", "opta": "alfalfa and clover", "optb": "soybean", "optc": "bean and lupine", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Denitrification may be distinguished as", "opta": "dissimilative", "optb": "assimilative", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "blue baby syndrome", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The conversion of molecular nitrogen into ammonia is known as", "opta": "nitrification", "optb": "denitrification", "optc": "nitrogen fixation", "optd": "ammonification", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The breakdown of cattle manure in biogas is accomplished by which of the following type of bacteria?", "opta": "Hydrolytic", "optb": "Transitional", "optc": "methanogenic", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following species of different genera of bacteria are not capable of transforming nitrate to nitrogen?", "opta": "Achromobacter", "optb": "Agrobacterium", "optc": "Alcaligenes", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Some microorganisms have the ability to increase the nitrogen content of soils, are called as", "opta": "nitrogen fixation", "optb": "denitrification", "optc": "nitrification", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nitrogen fixation", "opta": "changes the free nitrogen (N2) to a form usable by plants", "optb": "especially changes nitrogen compounds, mostly amines such as NH2", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "fix the free nitrogen (N2) by which it should not be usable by plants", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For rapid decomposition by microbes, the substrate should have a C/N ratio of", "opta": "10-20", "optb": "20-30", "optc": "30-40", "optd": "60-80", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which are the main source of biofertilisers?", "opta": "Cyanobacteria", "optb": "Bacillus", "optc": "Streptococcus", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The organisms responsible for the characteristic musty or earth odor of a freshly plowed field is/are", "opta": "Nocardia", "optb": "Streptomyces", "optc": "Micromonospora", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Denitrification is", "opta": "reduction of nitrate (NO3-) to nitrogen gas", "optb": "reduction of nitrate to organic nitrogen compounds", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "changing of atmospheric nitrogen (N2) to nitrogen compounds", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Degree of compost maturity can be assesed by", "opta": "infrared technique", "optb": "germination test", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The energy value of biogas is typically", "opta": "400-700 BTU/ft3", "optb": "1,000 BTU/ft3", "optc": "1500 BTU/ft3", "optd": "more than 5000 BTU/ft3", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The microbial ecosystem of soil includes", "opta": "biotic components of soil", "optb": "abiotic components of soil", "optc": "biotic and abiotic components of soil", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Denitrification is carried out", "opta": "usually by facultative anaerobes", "optb": "predominantly by Pseudomonas spp", "optc": "predominantly by Bacillus spp", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following soil microorganism is involved in the reduction of sulfates to H2S?", "opta": "Thiobacillus thiooxidans", "optb": "Desulfotomaculum", "optc": "Rhodospirillum", "optd": "Rhodomicrobium", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The diagnostic enzyme for nitrogen-fixing organisms is", "opta": "nitrogenase", "optb": "nitrate reductase", "optc": "nitrate oxidase", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following fungi on infecting crop roots can improve their uptake of phosphorus and other nutrients?", "opta": "Saccharomyces cerevisiae", "optb": "VA Mycorrhiza", "optc": "Candida torulopsis", "optd": "Aspergillus niger", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Syntrophism involves", "opta": "exchange of nutrients between two species", "optb": "exchange of nutrients among species", "optc": "no exchange of nutrients between two species", "optd": "no exchange of nutrients among species", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Assimilative denitrification is done by", "opta": "plants", "optb": "fungi", "optc": "prokaryotes", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}